So our last major topic is called many-to-many relationships and up till now everything that we've done
is what's called a one-to-many relationship and that is there are many tracks associated with one album,
there are many albums associated with one artist, there are many tracks associated with one genre
and you can think of labeling and as you look at data models they put little labels on each arrow
that tell you which end of the arrow is the many and which end of the arrow is the one
and so in this case the foreign key is pointing to there are many of these rows over here,
many rows that point to one row over here, so it's a many-to-one relationship.
There are various ways, sometimes I'll put two arrows at this end and one arrow at that end
but whatever it is, this kind of thing we've been showing is a many-to-one relationship
and that's probably the most common thing but there are times when you just can't model things
with the one-to-many relationship. So like if you have a mother and children, well that's a
many-to-one relationship and it's just fine and that works fine but sometimes you have a
many-to-many relationship in that there might be many books, one book has many authors and each
author has many books and so you don't have like the one side, there's no one and so you have to
end up building a table that what we call it, I call it a connector table, they call it a junction
table on Wikipedia but we need a little table that allows us to break a many-to-many relationship
into an effect, two many-to-one relationships and a connector table and so this is a connector table
so you could think of this as you know there are many many links here but we don't have a way to
model the many over here to here and so what you do is you basically say oh there's a lot of these
things, there's many that go to the one, the many that go to the one and then in here you sort of
create that many-ness that you want to create so it's probably just as easy to look at a sample of
this so let's imagine a learning management system where you're taking a class and there are some
people that are teachers and some people that are students and many students are members of many
classes, a student can be part of many classes and a class has many students in it so you can't really
find the one end and so what we do is we make a table called membership and in that table of
membership we actually often don't put a primary key in at all we simply put in two foreign keys
and if we're going to put a uniqueness constraint we put a combination of the two foreign keys as
the uniqueness constraint so we say there can be duplicate user IDs and duplicate course IDs but
there can only be you know user ID course ID combinations that has to be unique so you can make
unique be more than one one column and so if you imagine a course table and a user table there's a
user ID the name and email and the course has a title and an ID and then we have this little table
that just is the connector table that shows the points out and so we can expand this membership
so let's take a look at how that works so we're going to create some tables and the
these are very classic tables because these are the one end of it so these are the one end of it
so it has a primary key a title a logical key email there's a primary key for course and then
there's text so we add this unique to kind of indicate that it's a logical key we're not going
to allow ourselves to put any duplicates in here now that the connector database here is a table
member and it has two foreign keys user ID and artist course ID and you can even model some data
here so I'm going to model role which is going to be zero equals student and one equals instructor
and then I'm going to indicate that the primary key or uniqueness constraint is the combination
of the user ID and a course ID now when we say the primary key it both limits our ability to insert
duplicates but it also allows the database to optimize its scanning because it knows that that
combination is always unique and so it can organize its disk structure and storage structure
to understand how to look things up more efficiently knowing that once it's found a user ID course ID
combination it doesn't have to look any farther because they're unique and so all of these
contracts that we add speed things up save storage and makes things more efficient but in ways we
don't always know exactly how they happened and so let's go ahead and make these let's go ahead
and make these guys I think I will start with a new database I'm going to call it LMS for learning
management system no I don't really want to do that one and so I'm going to not create the table
I'm going to do everything in SQL and so let me see if it's in my cheat sheet nope that's not in
my cheat sheet so I have to fix the cheat sheet again for you by the time you see the cheat sheet
all these things will be in there so I'm going to go in here and I'm going to grab create table user
actually I'm going to grab them all watch this
grab them all highlight all these go over to SQLite browser blast them all in and then I'll
put a semicolon at the end of each one of the statements and I want to run them
so did I look does it look good yep yep yep so I got a course I got membership two foreign keys
and I got user so that all looks good okay so now we're going to have to insert some data in
and we're going to insert from the outside in and so we're going to just put the name and email
the ID will be automatically assigned for the users and we're going to do the same thing and
the ID and the courses will be automatically assigned so let me just grab all this stuff
go into SQL that has the semicolons at the end already for me thank you very much now I'm going
to run it and if I take a look at my data now I've got primary keys for the courses and I've got
primary keys for the users and I've got nothing in the membership table and I have to of course
have to remember what these values are because Jane is one and Ed is two and Sue is three right
and Python is one SQL is two is three and so when I go into membership I've got two foreign keys
here in a role and they just have to be for the course person combination and so it's a little
tricky to figure all this stuff out but again these are just numbers and if you look at these
numbers user ID course ID role well user ID one is in course one user ID is in course as the teacher
user ID two is in course one as the student etc etc etc so I'm making these connections by just
putting these little numbers in and once again conveniently I have all my semicolons perfectly
in place so I go to SQL and then I run that and then I take and I look at my membership data and
there it is so two foreign keys and a bit of data modeled at the connection that's the way we say
that the role is modeled at the connection so now we build all this stuff up we can write some queries
that take a look at this and so what we're going to do is we're going to look at who's in what course
and what role are they and we're going to sort this in a nice way so let's just take a quick look
at the code we're writing we're going to do a select from three tables the user name the member
role the course title so we're in effect we're not showing any of the foreign keys or the primary
keys we're going to go from the user table join to the member table join to the course table
this is pretty easy to write you know there are three tables you want to go across the on clause
is also very easy to write right the on clause models each of these connections where the members
user id is equal to the user's id and where the members course id is equal to the course id so
we're going to connect we're going to concatenate all three of these tables together but we're going
to only keep rows that where it matters now that this is not this role doesn't participate but we're
going to print that out and we're going to order it by the course title first and then the member
role second and the name third and so let's run that so we've reconnected it so ed's the teacher
of the php class sue is the student the php class jane is the teacher in the python class ed's a
student and sewer students in the python class ed's the teacher in the sql class and jane is
the student in the sql class and so we have many people are in there are many students in many
classes there and so we have modeled that but we model that with this sort of table and if you look
at a piece of software that i've written called sugi which is a standalone learning management
system that's built with learning tools you will see in anything we're in membership where we have
a we have a user table we have a context which is also the course table and then we have a
membership table and you look here's these foreign keys it's kind of like that's the many side that's
the one side many to one and so this you know this is now a an effect of many to many court
between these two but then it's modeled as a series of many to one many to one relationships
and you see this all the time in all kinds of things where membership or other kinds of things
are necessary many to one how many to many so with all that there's so much to learn it's it's both
easy and complex at the same time it's easy when someone shows you how to do it but at some point
you will learn how to build database models and you realize oh it wasn't so bad it takes a while
to get used to them this really just is a quick walk but the the bottom line is the what we just
did seems like it was wow that's nice do you really have to do that and the answer is if you're going
to scale it all you absolutely have to because you simply can't read and write data sequentially
you can't read through a update one little piece of data in a file by reading all the way through
and then writing a new copy of the file that could take seconds and in a system like an online system
you get a hundredth of a second to do something like that and the databases make it so that
happens in a thousandth of a second so you ultimately you simply have to take advantage
of this you just can't if you're going to modify data you can read data from flat files but even
if you're going to read a lot of data if it's big it slows down terribly so it might seem like
there's a trade-off that you could debate whether this is worth it but if you're going to deal with
a lot of data it's you've got no choice it's really not as much a trade-off as you think so
this has been a quick romp through databases we talked a little bit about indexes there are
constraints we talked a little bit the not null stuff we've talked about that the uniqueness
that's a constraint another whole area is what's called transactions and that's the locking of
little areas so you can read an area then lock it and then update it to make sure no one else reads
it and and so they make sure they either get the the version before you looked at it or before you
change it or after you change it and so that's how you make sure that you can't do things having to
do with bank account balances and get yourself in trouble so these are a lot of sql it's really
fascinating sql is a fascinating thing to use and learn and performance tune and enjoy so
relational databases are cool this gets us started the the big thing is don't allow replication
vertically of string data pull that out into a separate table establish a primary key and
then have foreign keys that point to that primary key it is not just how much data you store it's
sort of a compression way as a way of compressing data you might think strings take no data but they
do numbers take a lot less data and it's both how much data that's stored but also how much data has
to be scanned and that way joins work that's part of the magic of why oracles such a such a successful
company it's a bit of art form and it's something that you can work your whole life and always get better at
(upbeat music)